Finding Aid for Turner Geriatric Clinic records, 1979-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Turner Geriatric Clinic records 1979-2009, 1990-2008
Turner Geriatric Clinic.
9 linear feet
2013061 Bimu C 502 2
The Turner Geriatric Clinic was established in 1978 as an extension of the University of Michigan Hospital and is devoted to the medical and social care of the elderly. The collection ranges from 1979 to 2009 (bulk 1990-2008) and contains material on community and social work programs, including photographs, video and audio cassettes, information on programs sponsored by the Center, publications, and material from the U.S.-Japan Training Institute.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Turner Geriatric Clinic (Donor No. 10450 ) in November 2010.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Turner Geriatric Clinic records are open without restriction.
Ivan Duff, a rheumatologist at the University of Michigan, began research into the treatment and care of elderly patients in his practice. Upon learning that psychological, emotional, and social problems affected their health, he initiated programs to emphasize the treatment of these things, and in doing so, pushed for the creation of a clinic dedicated to the prevention and treatment of illness in the elderly while also improving their quality of life. A vote from the University of Michigan Hospital community was taken to determine the necessity of such a clinic. With an endowment from Scott and Amy Prudden Turner that was given to the University Hospital to be used for the benefit of older adults, the Turner Geriatric Clinic was started in 1978. The clinic was designed to offer a wide range of primary health services for elderly patients, including ophthalmology, psychiatry, nursing, physical rehabilitation, dentistry, and education. Duff was appointed the first director and one of his other co-workers, Florence Tillman, was the first nurse of the clinic. Ruth Campbell was employed as a social worker and she worked with Duff to create a committee of elderly people to serve as advisors, friends, and supporters to their peers. The clinic has since hired more people and brought in many volunteers to help with programs. The programs have been educational and supportive, and social programs, including writing circles, have also attracted a large group of people. The clinic distinguishes itself from other clinics like it by offering programs that provide a social support system for non-medical influences in patient's health.
With the growing popularity and success of the Turner Geriatric Clinic, the Turner Senior Resource Center was added in 1998. It serves as an extension of the clinic to house community programs and services. One very successful program from the Center is the Silver Club, a program for seniors with memory loss.
The collection consists of materials from the Turner Geriatric Clinic that begins when the Center was established in 1979 and ends with records from 2009, with the bulk covering 1990-2008. The collection contains eight series: Personal Files, Photographs, Programs, Publications, Publicity, Topical Files, U.S.-Japan Institute, and Audio-Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Turner Geriatric Clinic.; Geriatrics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gerontology--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Older people--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Older people--Counseling of--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Older people--Japan.; University of Michigan. Division of Gerontology.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Gerontology--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Older people--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Older people--Japan.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Older people--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Korean War, 1950-1953--Prisoners and prisons, North Korea.; Fletcher, Robert W.
Contributors:
Campbell, Ruth.; Duff, Ivan Francis, 1915-
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Videotapes.
- Personal Files
  The Personal Files (0.3 linear feet) series contains information on individuals who were part of the staff of the Geriatric Center, and on elderly individuals who were members of the center. This includes people such as Alma Wooll who was heavily involved in the Center's events. Included within each file are correspondence, general documents, and information on events or programs that the individual was a part of.
  - Alma Ford Wooll (Box 1)
  - Bernhard Chomet 1991-1995, 2000, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Beverly Gershowitz 2007 (Box 1)
  - Florence Tillman 2002 (Box 1)
  - Ivan Duff 1994 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs (0.3 linear feet) series contains a variety of photos from specific events in the Center, as well as a miscellaneous folder. There are photographs from the Living History program that the Center put on, photographs from the Nursing Home Enrichment program, and photographs from the Senior Sing and Swing event.
  - Living History -- Remembering Ypsilanti 1990 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Nursing Home Enrichment 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Senior Sing and Swing 1984 (Box 1)
- Programs
  The Programs (0.9 linear feet) series contains information on events, workshops, and seminars that the Geriatric Center hosted or sponsored. Most files contain generic information, flyers, and correspondence about each program. Programs include the Art Gallery 55+ event where the elderly showcased their personal artwork, the Forgiveness Group where participants attended weekly seminars on how to forgive others and themselves, and the Coming of Age Event when the Center entered into its 21st year of service.
  - Art Gallery 55+ 2003 (Box 1)
  - Arts of Citizenship Program 1999 (Box 1)
  - Ask the Doctor 1997, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Caregiver Events 1996, 2001-2002, 2004 undated (Box 1)
  - Caregiver's Fair 2003 (Box 1)
  - Caring for Aging Relatives Seminar 2001, 2006-2008, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Challenge Program 1994 (Box 1)
  - Coming of Age Event 1999 (Box 1)
  - Community Based Outreach 1994 (Box 1)
  - Courthouse Square Outreach 1996 (Box 1)
  - Forgiveness Group 2002, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - For Men Only 1997 (Box 2)
  - Health Fair for Seniors 1984-1987, 1989, 1993, 2003 undated (Box 2)
  - If You Ask Me, I'll Tell You 2000 (Box 2)
  - Life is a Story 2005 (Box 2)
  - Life Worth Living Conference 1997 (Box 2)
  - The Lively Mind 1988 (Box 2)
  - Living History -- Remembering Ypsilanti 1990 (Box 2)
  - Living History -- Sharing Memories of the Chelsea Area 1991 (Box 2)
  - Living with Hearing Loss 2003, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Martin Luther King Jr. Day 2000, 2003-2005 (Box 2)
  - Neighbor to Neighbor (Box 2)
  - Senior Oral History Project 1997 (Box 2)
  - Shaking the Blues 2001 (Box 2)
  - Social Work Class 1999 (Box 2)
  - Social Work Programs 1994 (Box 2)
  - Summer Senior Dance 2003 (Box 2)
  - Writing Groups 1988 (Box 2)
- Publications
  The Publications (1.5 linear feet) series contains books and articles produced by the Center itself, or by the people attending the programs at the Center. Included are the publications for Caring for Your Aging Relatives, a seminar for the family members of the elderly, the "Never Say Never" publications written by the Center's writing group, and a collection of poetry by Arvil Brown.
  - African American Health Guide 1999 (Box 2)
  - "Caring: A Guide for Elder Companions," 1994 (Box 2)
  - "Caring for Aging Relatives," 1998, 2002-2004, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - "Collected Poems and One Essay" by Kathleen Maddox 1995 (Box 2)
  - "Come Be My Love" by Anne-Marie Nilsen (Box 2)
  - Dealing with the Doldrums 1997 (Box 3)
  - Divorce in Later Life (Box 3)
  - Entrepreneurship in Social Work 1988 (Box 3)
  - "For John Hathaway," 1994 (Box 3)
  - "Grand Ma Tells with Love" (Box 3)
  - Life History of Jean Lynn Barnard (Box 3)
  - Low Vision and Visual Rehabilitation 2001 (Box 3)
  - "Martin's Odyssey," 1993 (Box 3)
  - Memory Stimulation Groups in the Nursing Home Center 1988 (Box 3)
  - Multi-disciplinary Assessment (Box 3)
  - "My Autobiography" by Ardith King 1992 (Box 3)
  - "Never Say Never," 1984, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - "Never Say Never II," 1991 (Box 3)
  - Newsletter 1986-1988 (Box 3)
  - Nursing Facility Diversion: Mobilizing Residents, Families and Resources to Facilitate Return to Community Living 2004 (Box 3)
  - "The Passing Snow," 1988 (Box 3)
  - Peer Support for Older Adults 1981 (Box 3)
  - People with Visual Impairment 1983 (Box 3)
  - Poems by Arvil Brown 1993 (Box 3)
  - Poems by Bernhard Chomet (Box 3)
  - "Sam's Princess," 1988 (Box 3)
  - "Storywriter," 1989 (Box 3)
  - Where to Turn: A Guide to Washtenaw County Programs and Services for People Over 60 1992, 1995, 1997-1998, 2001 (Box 3)
  - A Writer's Favorite Cookbook 1999 (Box 3)
- Publicity
  The Publicity (0.7 linear feet) series contains general articles, flyers, and brochures for the Geriatrics Center. A set of folders, titled Programs and Events, are organized chronologically and contain flyers and information on the various programs and events held at the Center throughout each year.
  - Articles 1983, 1987-1991, 1993 undated (Box 4)
  - Brochures 1991, 2003 undated (Box 4)
  - Flyers 1991-1994, 1998-2003, 2008 undated (Box 4)
  - Marketing 2000, 2002-2003 (Box 4)
  - Program Highlights (Box 4)
  - Programs and Events 1980-1981, 1986-1994, 1996-2007, 18 folders (Box 4)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (1.3 linear feet) series contains information on fundraising campaigns, correspondence, partner associations, scrapbooks, awards given by the Center, and the history of the Center, among various other files relating to elder issues.
  - Advisory Board 1989, 1991-1995, 2005-2008, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Alzheimer's Association 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - Artwork (Box 4)
  - Award for Excellence in Social Work 2003, 2005, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Brookhaven Manor 2000 (Box 4)
  - Cancer Center 1996 (Box 4)
  - Caregivers 2000, 2003-2005 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1979, 1985, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Eldercare Crisis 2009 (Box 5)
  - Flu Vaccine 2003 (Box 5)
  - Fundraising Committee 1998-2006, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - History of Center (Box 5)
  - Housing Bureau for Seniors 1983 (Box 5)
  - Lifetime Achievement Award 1999, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Mail Fundraising Campaign 1994, 1998-2006 (Box 5)
  - Minority Access Committee 1990-1991, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Needs Assessment 1997, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Nursing Home Group 2001 (Box 5)
  - Peer Counselors 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - Proposals 1995-1997 (Box 5)
  - Riverview Nursing Home 2001 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Senior Players Drama Troupe 1997 (Box 5)
  - Social Work Proposal 1991 (Box 5)
  - Surveys 1995-1998 (Box 5)
  - Travel 2004 undated (Box 5)
  - Turner Senior Resource Center Space Expansion 2001-2002 (Box 5)
- US-Japan Institute
  The U.S.-Japan Institute (2.1 linear feet) series contains the guidebooks and reports for the years of the geriatrics training program held in Japan. The U.S.-Japan Training Institute in Geriatric Care was created in 1992 by the Japanese Ministry of Health and Welfare entering into a partnership with the University of Michigan Geriatrics Center. It was called for due to the rising life expectancy of people in Japan and the need to provide both public and private services to the elderly. The guidebooks in the series are organized chronologically and the English copies are separated from the Japanese copies.
  - General Information (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-English 1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-English 1993, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-Japanese 1993 (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-English 1994 (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-Japanese 1994, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-English 1995, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-Japanese 1995, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-English 1996, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-Japanese 1996, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Guidebook-English 1997, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Guidebook-Japanese 1997, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Guidebook-English 1999 (Box 7)
  - Guidebook-Japanese 1999 (Box 7)
  - "Health and Welfare for the Elderly" (Box 7)
  - Improving Quality of Care for People with Dementia and their Caregivers Conference-English 2007 (Box 7)
  - Improving Quality of Care for People with Dementia and their Caregivers Conference-Japanese 2007 (Box 7)
  - Interim Report 2008 (Box 7)
  - Photographs (Box 7)
  - Program Proposal 2006-2008, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Publicity 2007-2008 (Box 7)
  - Report 1-3 1992-1994 (Box 7)
  - Report 4-5 and 9 1995-1996, 2000 (Box 7)
  - Report Year 1 2007-2008 (Box 7)
  - Report Year 2 2008-2009, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Seminar 2007 (Box 8)
  - Seminar Program 1993, 1995-1996, 1998-1999 (Box 8)
  - Steering Committee 2007 (Box 8)
- Audio-Visual Material
  The Audio-Visual Materials (1.9 linear feet) series contains two subseries. The first, Videocassettes, contains various VHS cassettes produced by the Center and the elderly people involved in it, including videos on training programs and tapes from the Japanese Training Institute. The second subseries, Audiocassettes, contains interview tapes organized alphabetically by the last name of the interviewee or the name of the organization being interviewed. The interviews were conducted as part of a life history project designed to have subjects discuss their lives and experiences.
  - Videocassettes
    - African American Alzheimer Program-Caregivers and Spirituality 1999 (Box 8)
    - "The Basics of Peer Counseling," 1991 (Box 8)
    - "The Geriatric Interdisciplinary Team Training Program, Video Case Study #2: Mr. Rosario," 1997 (Box 8)
    - "The Geriatric Interdisciplinary Team Training Program, Video Case Study #4: Mr. Jenkins," 1997 (Box 8)
    - "The Geriatric Interdisciplinary Team Training Program, Video Case Study #5: The Tsai's," 1997 (Box 8)
    - "Harvesting Meaning in Life: A View from the Garden," 2002 (Box 8)
    - "Having Our Say: The Delany Sisters' First 100 Years," 1997 (Box 8)
    - "Life Worth Living," 1997, 4 tapes (Box 8)
    - Turner Clinic Peer Ed (Box 8)
    - Opening Ceremony of NPO Michigan Network 2002 (Japanese) (Box 8)
    - "Patient Empowerment Vignettes Case #8," 2001 (Box 8)
    - "Pioneers of Aging: Living Well in Later Life," 1996 (Japanese) (Box 8)
    - "Pioneers of Aging: Living Well in Later Life," 1999 (Box 8)
    - Plaque Ceremony of Mr. Fujisawa 2002 (Box 8)
    - "United Nations International Year of Older Persons," 1999 (Box 8)
  - Audiocassettes
    - Allen, Leola -- Life Review 1993, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - Ann Arbor Community Center Group -- Life History Project 1992, 6 tapes (Box 9)
    - Bailey, Evelyn -- Life Review 1993, 5 tapes (Box 9)
    - Baker Commons Group -- Life History Project 1993, 6 tapes (Box 9)
    - Bostic, Mr. F -- Life Review 1992 (Box 9)
    - Brien, Bannie -- Life History 1993, 3 tapes (Box 9)
    - Byrd, Beatrice 1992 (Box 9)
    - Cash, William -- Life Review 1993, 5 tapes (Box 9)
    - Fletcher, Robert -- Korean Prisoner of War 1993-1994, 3 tapes (Box 9)
    - Golden Rule Friendship Club -- Life History Project 1993, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - Helfrich, Faye 1993, 3 tapes (Box 9)
    - Henderson, Viola -- Life Review 1993, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - Heroes Group -- Life History Project 1992, 6 tapes (Box 9)
    - Knox, Annie 1993, 2 tapes (Box 9)
    - Kress, Dorothy -- Life Review 1992, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - Lindstrom, Hildegard -- Life Review 1993, 2 tapes (Box 9)
    - Lovejoy, Bessie 1993, 2 tapes (Box 9)
    - Mack, Dorothy -- Life Review 1993, 2 tapes (Box 9)
    - Marshall, Ruthe -- Life History 1993, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - New Hope Baptist Church Group -- Life History Project 1993, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - Overby, Mrs 1993, 3 tapes (Box 9)
    - Patton, Dubois -- Life Review 1993 (Box 9)
    - Rodntz, Christian -- Journal 1986 (Box 9)
    - Schwimmer, Helen -- Life Review 1993, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - Shelton, Woodrow -- Life Review 1992-1993, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - Smith, Shirley -- Life Review 1993, 5 tapes (Box 9)
    - Spann, Mrs. Paul 1992, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - Spann, Rev. Paul 1993, 2 tapes (Box 9)
    - Thomas, Austin M. -- Life History 1992, 3 tapes (Box 9)
    - Thurston 1992, 4 tapes (Box 9)
    - Towne Center Place -- Life History Project 1993, 6 tapes (Box 9)
    - Wagman 1992, 3 tapes (Box 9)
    - Wilson, Floy -- Life Review (Box 9)